COTSEN4 COTSEN4
Cotsen Children's Library
Margaret K. McElderry Papers
1900
Cotsen Children's Library
COTSEN4
1.0 (1 box)
- Chester Aaron, 1976 - 1977
  - Hello to Bodega, 1976
    Scope and Contents note
    Ellen Levine Literary Agency - first at Curtis Brown Aaron's book An American Ghost (what is the correspondence about?); Working on Spill and Calico jacket by Bob Ziering MKM's visit to Aaron in summer 1975 - where? both major and minor revisions Edwin Honig's poem "Bodega, Goodbye" film interest searching for British options; interest from Denmark; paperback reprinting lots of reviews; lots of stuff about sending author copies, Bodega Volunteer Fire Co fundraiser; problem about sending review copies; confusion about how many review copies would be sent - author upset interest from Denmark and film rights (Compass Productions) Judy Long's own book Volunteer Spring
    Arrangement note
    Chronological
  - Spill, 1977
    working on at the same time as Hello to Bodega includes chunks of the manuscript with revision in blue pencil by MKM Aaron's trip to NYC in December 1976
    Film interest, Japanese, Norwegian and British interest Aaron's 1977 trip to Israel - on a National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship Michael Mariano did the jacket references to an angry letter in summer 77 but no evidence of the letter itself
- Joan Walsh Anglund
  - Goodbye, Yesterday, 1974
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry and Anglund regarding this book of poetry for adults. The file is less complete than many others in collection, including only letters from after the book was published, as well as a contract. Most of the correspondence concerns promotion and book sales: other correspondents include Anglund's husband Robert; Sir William Collins of Collins Publishers, London; and Faith Brunson of Rich's, Inc. in Atlanta, GA. Includes a handwritten note with drawing from Anglund to McElderry.
- Edward Ardizzone, 1979
  - Ardizzone's Hans Andersen, 1979
    Correspondence between McElderry, Judy Long and three people at Andre Deutsch London (Anne-Louise Fisher, Pamela Royds and Polly Dunnett), regarding the American publication of fourteen Hans Christian Andersen stories illustrated by Ardizzone. There is no direct correspondence with Ardizzone. Letters between McElderry and Royds also discuss Ardizzone's work on illustrations of Joseph Jacob's English Fairy Tales, Ardizzone's death in November 1979, David McPhail's Captain Toad and the Motorbike and joint work with Erik Blegvad. There are also letters between McElderry and Laura Cecil, Ardizzone's agent; in addition to Ardizzone they discuss Irina Hale's Chocolate Mouse and Sugar Pig, Niki Daly's Vim the Rag Mouse and Daly's illustrations for Maybe It's a Tiger by Kathleen Hersom.
- Lenore and Erik Blegvad, 1970 - 1980
  - Burnie's Hill: A Traditional Rhyme, illustrated by Erik Blegvad, 1977
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Erik and Lenore Blegvad, Judy Long, and two representatives of Collins Publishers, Linda Davis and Linda Pooley, regarding Burnie's Hill, a traditional British rhyme illustrated by Erik Blegvad. Collins published the book in the UK. Correspondence is fairly limited; topics include contract discussions and how to attribute the text. There is also much discussion of The Winter Bear, a Ruth Craft text published with Blegvad's illustrations two years before and reprinted around the same time as the publication of Burnie's Hill.
  - Hark! Hark! The Dogs Do Bark, and Other Rhymes about Dogs, chosen by Lenore Blegvad and illustrated by Erik Blegvad, 1976
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Lenore and Erik Blegvad, Judy Long, and Julia McRae at Hamish Hamilton, which published the book in the UK, regarding this illustrated book of poetry, intended as a companion to the Blegvad's earlier Mittens for Kittens. Topics include contract negotiations, arrangement and illustration of poems, the delay of the original art in customs, interest in translation from South African and Japanese firms, and the accidental lamination of the book's cover. Other work of the Blegvads is also discussed, including Mittens for Kittens, illustrations for Ruth Craft's The Winter Bear, other potential nursery rhyme projects, an exhibition of Lenore's artwork at a London gallery, and a completed but unnamed manuscript written by Lenore.
  - Mittens for Kittens
    poems selected from the public domain by Lenore and illustrated by Erik whether to print jointly or separately with Hamish Hamilton (Julia MacRae) - business trouble at HH; also with Michael Brown re reproduction - misunderstanding about figured between production departments (David Rogers at Atheneum); delay of publication day due to printing in England exactly which poems to include and where to skip verses
    the usual trouble with the mail discussion of new book on dogs Linda Davis at Collins interested in taking it (not knowing about agreement with HH) - also Let's Marry Said the Cherry if Macmillan turns it down; Gwen Marsh at Dent also interested interest from Sweden enthusiasm from John Leibfried Jr., a PA bookseller interest in a recording from American Printing House for the Blind (Louisville, KY) concern about royalties
    Watergate, children (Peter and Kristoffer) other authors: Robert Norton and Trina Schart Hyman; N.M. Bodecker - son Niels visiting the Blegvads; Oates of Eden by William Corlett
    Barbara Douglas, MKM secretary
  - General Correspondence, 1972-1978
    Correspondence between McElderry and the Blegvads not related to any of the above titles. Projects with Erik include his interest in illustrating Hans Christian Andersen stories and Danish fairy tales, his illustrations for N.M. Bodecker's The Mushroom Center Disaster and Let's Marry Said the Cherry, Joan Phipson's Polly's Tiger, Ruth Craft's The Winter Bear, and the jacket illustration for Nina Beachcroft's Well Met By Watchlight. Projects with Lenore include a number of ideas or manuscripts ultimately rejected by McElderry, including a beginner's book called "Mr. Tiger, In and Out," a novel called "Macaroons and Mystery," and a version of an old French folktale called "The Village That Almost Fell into the Sea." They also discuss the publication of Lenore's Moon-Watch Summer by Harcourt, and a planned English exhibition of her work (1974). Related correspondence with Julia McRae at Hamish Hamilton is also included in the file. Personal topics include travel and children, the possibility of one of McElderry's friends renting the Blegvad's London flat for the summer, whether McElderry will consider work by a few of Lenore's friends, and the promotion of Irene Haas's The Maggie B.
- Max Bolliger, 1982
  - The Lonely Prince, 1982
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Judy Long, representatives of Artemis Verlag (Bruno Mariacher and Rosemarie Roth), and representatives of Methuen London (Rosemary Martin), regarding Bolliger's The Lonely Prince, illustrated by Jürg Obrist. There is no correspondence with Bolliger, but there are a few letters from Obrist, who pitched the book to Atheneum. Though Obrist initially approached McElderry, Jean Karl considered it for her list before it was passed back to McElderry due to cost concerns. Correspondence includes several working translations of the story, originally written in German with the title "Heinrich;" other topics include negotiation for open market distribution rights, printing and binding trouble, accounting difficulties between Atheneum and Artemis, and reprinting of the work. Later correspondence with Methuen also regards Obrist's The Miser Who Wanted the Sun.
- Lucy Boston, 1971-1985
  - The Fossil Snake, 1974-1979; 69.0
    Folder contains primarily correspondence, both personal and professional, with/regarding the following individuals: Lucy Boston, Peter Boston, Dr. Sibylle Goller, Reet Nelis (The Bodley Head), Stephanie Ives (secretary to Reet Nelis), Barbara Elleman (American Library Association), Margaret Clark (The Bodley Head), Marianne Carus (Cricket Magazine), Jane Jordan Browne, Adele Leone Hull (Pocket Books), Jane Bloomfield (secretary to Reet Nelis). All correspondence is related to the publication of The Fossil Snake (1975), written by Lucy Boston and illustrated by Peter Boston. Because The Fossil Snake was published in both the US and the UK, a significant portion of the correspondence is between McElderry and editors at the UK publishing house (The Bodley Head), regarding the dual publication process. Specific professional topics discussed include jacket illustrations, line edits to the manuscript, conversions between British slang and US slang, the terms of Lucy Boston's contract, the serialization of the book in Cricket Magazine, and an inquiry about optioning movie rights. Personal topics discussed include the death of McElderry's husband, repairs to her apartment after a pipe burst, and the economic climate (including its effect on the publishing world).
  - The Guardians of the House, 1974
    DESCRIPTION HERE
  - Perverse and Foolish, 1978-1980; 105.0 items
    Folder contains primarily correspondence, both personal and professional, with/regarding the following individuals: Lucy Boston, Margaret Clark (The Bodley Head), Reet Nelis (The Bodley Head), Harry Ford, Siu Zimmerman, Clifton Fadiman, and Judy Long. All correspondence is related to the publication of Perverse and Foolish (1979), a memoir by Lucy Boston. Because the book was published in both the US and the UK, a significant portion of the correspondence is between McElderry and editors at the UK publishing house (The Bodley Head), regarding the dual publication process. Specific professional topics discussed include the release schedule, jacket copy, line edits to the manuscript, and Boston's concerns about bad reviews once the book was released. Specific personal topics discussed include McElderry breaking her foot, Christmas celebrations, and McElderry's office moving to a new building. Accompanying the correspondence are the contracts for Perverse and Foolish.
  - The Stones of Green Knowe, 1975-1985; 103.0 items
    Folder contains primarily correspondence, both personal and professional, with/regarding the following individuals: Lucy Boston, Margaret Clark (The Bodley Head), Ellen Suffern, Alice K. Wilson (California State College), Susan Sevray, Mrs. Marshall Bassick, Reet Nelis (The Bodley Head), Peter Boston, and Judy Taylor (The Bodley Head). All correspondence is related to the publication of The Stones of Green Knowe (1976), written by Lucy Boston and illustrated by Peter Boston. Because the book was published in both the US and the UK, a significant portion of the correspondence is between McElderry and editors at the UK publishing house (The Bodley Head), regarding the dual publication process. Specific professional topics discussed include payment for Peter Boston's artwork and Atheneum's share of composition costs, reviews of the book, Boston's poetry and the impossibility of getting it published, visitors to Green Knowe, the heat wave in the UK during the summer of '76, Peter Boston redrawing particular illustrations, jacket design, Frank Boston's accident while horseback riding, and the terms of Boston's contract. Specific professional topics discussed include Boston's plans for more Green Knowe titles in the future, type-setting for the book, Peter Boston's illustrations, line edits to the manuscript, Boston's frustrations with some of McElderry's suggested changes and her refusal to make them, the publication of the title by Bodley Head rather than Faber (publisher of the previous Green Knowe books) and the accompanying challenges of making that shift. Specific personal topics discussed include McElderry's holiday, Storer's illness, and the concerts Boston was hosting. Accompanying the correspondence in pt. 2 are the contracts for The Stones of Green Knowe.
  - General Correpondence, pt. 1, 1971-October 1973; 74.0 items
    Chronological order. Pt. 1 contains correspondence from 1971 to 1977.
    Folder contains primarily correspondence, both personal and professional, with/regarding the following individuals: Lucy Boston, Margaret Clark (The Bodley Head), Peter Boston, Elizabeth Vellacott, and Elling Aannestad. Specific professional topics discussed include Boston's decision to move from Faber to Bodley Head, her transition between the two publishing houses, McElderry's transition from Harcourt to Atheneum, and Boston's work on her memoirs. Specific personal topics discussed include Boston's birthday presents and celebration, work on Peter Boston's house, and Watergate.
  - General Correspondence, pt. 2, November 1973-1976; 96.0 items
    Chronological. Pt. 2 contains correspondence from 11977-1984.
    Folder contains primarily correspondence, both personal and professional, with the following individuals: Lucy Boston, Margaret Clark (The Bodley Head), Peter Boston, Elizabeth Vellacott, Sally McGuire, J.L. Boele van Hensbroek, and Marianne Carus (Cricket Magazine). Specific professional topics discussed include the Newberry Award recipients, edits to various books by Boston, a list of American words/phrases that might not have British equivalents, and the return of original artwork to Peter Boston. Specific personal topics discussed include McElderry sitting for a portrait, McElderry's search for rope-soled espadrilles, and the lack of heat in Boston's house.
- John Branfield, 1980
  - The Fox in Winter, 1982
    Correspondence primarily between agents at Atheneum (McElderry, Judy Long, associate editor Paula Schwartz, and designer Felicia Bond), agents at Victor Gollancz (Joanna Goldsworthy and Stephen Bray), and agents at Curtis Brown (Marilyn Marlow) regarding Branfield's novel about the friendship between a teenage girl and an elderly man. There is also correspondence between Branfield and McElderry. The book was originally published in the UK by Victor Gollancz and picked up by Atheneum. Correspondence topics include edits for the American edition, including language changes, discussion of the work's title, design for the American edition, reviews, motion picture interest and the novel's consideration for a Carnegie Medal. File also includes a copy of Victor Gollancz's complete 1982 list.
- Elizabeth Bridgman, 1977
  - All the Little Bunnies
    Correspondence primarily between Bridgman, McElderry, and Judy Long regarding Bridgman's illustrated counting book All the Little Bunnies. Topics include the book's design, a Christmas story written by Bridgman, a potential project called "Lazy Lion and Little Dog," Bridgman's illustrations for a book by Joan Kahn, and Judy Long's wedding. There is additional correspondence with William Heinemann Ltd., Japan UNI and Xerox regarding foreign publishing and paperback editions of the book. File also includes a printer's proof of one of the illustrations.
- Ruth Brindze, 1975
  - Look How Many People Wear Glasses: The Magic of Lenses, 1975
    Correspondence between Brindze, McElderry, and Judy Long, regarding the non-fiction book Look How Many People Wear Glasses. Topics include edits to the manuscript, discussion of the illustrations, and reactions to the book from eye doctors and other professionals. McElderry and Brindze also discuss Brindze's interest in writing a book about lighthouses. Additionally, there is correspondence with members of the New York Academy of Sciences, which gave the book an Honorable Mention in its Science Book Award program, and with Patrick Hardy of Kestrel Young Books, which considered publishing the title in the UK.
- Marcia Brown
  - General correspondence, 1971-1972
    General correspondence between Brown and McElderry. They discuss their mutual disappointment with the printing of Brown's book The Bun (published by Harcourt Brace), the possibility of a picture book by Brown's neighbor, and a visit between Brown and Susan Cooper.
- Emerson and David Coatsworth, 1980
  - Adventures of Nanabush: Ojibway Indian Stories
    working with Jonathan Lovat Dickson at Doubleday Canada shopping for English copublishers but no dice - tried Macmillian, Bodley Head and Julia McRae Children's books Francis Kagige illustrated MKM sends copies of Susan Cooper's books to Dickson's daughter, "book godmother" letter from a reader saying pages missing/out of order; MKM sends new copy includes materials related to cover illustration
- Bill Crofut, 1975
  - The Moon on the One Hand
- Jane Curry, 1971 - 1988
  - The Bassumtyte Treasure, 1978
  - The Birdstones, 1977
  - Ghost Lane, 1979
  - The Magical Cupboard, 1976
  - Poor Tom's Ghost, 1977
  - The Lost Farm, 1974
  - Shadow Dancers, 1983
  - The Watchers, 1975
  - The Wolves of Aam, 1981
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Papers, 1971 September 14-1980 June 17
- Douglas F. Davis, 1980
  - The Lion's Tail
    story about the point at the end of the lion's tail correspondence begins with questions about whether this is a real Masai folktale (no, but based on creation myth); Margaret consulted with Harriet Brown, a black children's librarian, about whether this was an acceptable sort of thing hoping to work with Leo and Diane Dillon, husband and wife team of illustrators MKM read his children's novel, "The Star Tree"; also version of Sufi tale "The Prince and the Sorceress"; also picture book idea "There's An Elephant in the Garage" (published by Dutton), "The Magnificent Prin"; "The Secret in the Bottle" delay in schedule because of business of Dillons; eventually cancel contract in November 1978 -- too busy; Ron Himler instead finally -- line edits full mock-up of the book with notes from the designer Shopping to England and South Africa
- Eleanor Estes, 1971 January 7 - 1983 March 11
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1981
    General correspondence between Estes and McElderry. Many of the letters regard family: a library school recommendation for Estes's daughter Helena written by McElderry; the heart attacks of Estes's brother Clarence; the death of brain cancer of Helena's husband Stephen Haeseler; and reports of vacations, including a 1979 trip to Spain and Tangiers in which Estes and her husband visited with authors Virginia Sorensen and Alec Waugh. Related to Estes's work, correspondence topics include Estes's growing dissatisfaction with Harcourt Brace Jovanovich; reviews of The Tunnel of Hugsy Goode; Estes's fanmail; whether Estes should illustrate Ann Warren Griffith's story "The Bed Book"; concerns about royalties; submission of work for potential publication including "Jimmy Mannikin," based on stories Estes wrote for Helena, and "The Flea Circus," originally published in Cricket Magazine; a speech Estes gave in appreciation of children's librarian and author Anne Carroll Moore; and discussion about whether Estes should donate her personal archive to the Kerlan Collection at the University of Minnesota. There are also a number of poems written by Estes to McElderry, including "Sad Ballad of an Analogous Man," about Sidney Long, written after he wrote a bad review of Hugsy Goode in the New York Times (spring 1972), and "There once was a girl in Barbados," written after McElderry's vacation to Barbados (April 5, 1975).
  - The Coat Hanger Christmas Tree
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Estes, McElderry's secretaries Florence Sczesny and Judy Long, and illustrator Susanne Suba about this story of a girl whose mother does not want the family to have a Christmas tree. The book was Estes's first with McElderry at Atheneum; the two had worked together when McElderry was at Harcourt Brace Jovanovich and the file includes correspodence with William Jovanovich regarding the Estes's requested release from her contract with the firm. Other topics of correspondence include much discussion of the book's drawings: McElderry and Estes considered Edward Ardizzone, Cyndy Szekeres, and Trina Schart Hyman before choosing Susanne Suba, and Estes was initially unhappy with the drawings, though she never communicated this to Suba. McElderry and Estes also discuss line edits to the manuscipt, trim size and font, and the terms of Estes's contract. Estes had recently moved to New Haven, CT, and she and McElderry talk about which bookshops to market to and how to get Estes involved at the Yale Co-Op. Other correspondence includes McElderry shopping the book to English publishers, including Bodley Head, Longman Young, Lutterworth Press, William Heinemann, and Ernest Benn, Ltd., and to Shigeo Watanabe and the Charles E. Tuttle, Co. in Japan. Oxford University Press eventually bought the English rights, and there are several letters between McElderry and editor Paul Binding; the two also discuss The Moon on the One Hand by Bill Crofut, OUP books McElderry would like to see, the possibility of doing a joint children's book project with Reynolds Price, and a late payment from OUP to Susanne Suba. Other promotional topics include the book's selection by the Junior Literary Guild, permission for Miller-Brody Productions to use images from it in a "Meet the Newbery Author" filmstrip, interest in a German translation from Obelisk, interest from Women's Day Magazine, and a letter from a schoolteacher asking for biographical information about Estes. In 1979, McElderry wrote to Estes to ask if Atheneum could lower her royalties in order to keep the book in print. Additional topics include whether Estes should get an agent to handle movie and television rights for her work, putting together a biographical pamphlet on Estes, and the launch party for Cricket Magazine. The two also talk about Estes's husband's various accidents and health issues and the death of her brother Clarence, as well as Lucy Boston's chapter on McElderry's wedding in her book Memory of a House.
  - The Lost Umbrella of Kim Chu
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Estes, McElderry's secretary, and later editor, Judy Long, and illustrator Jacqueline Ayer regarding this story about a girl who loses her father's umbrella in New York City's Chinatown. Topics include McElderry's general suggestions for the manuscript, line edits, and layout for the book, as well as the time crunch to publish by fall 1978 (Estes had hoped to work in person with both McElderry and Ayer, but time did not permit). Before McElderry and Estes chose Ayer as the illustrator, they considered Sag Harbor-based artist Joan Baren; the file includes xeroxes of her character sketches, but Estes found the drawings too stylized and potentially racially offensive. Also included are a map of Kim's home drawn by Estes (undated), and a limerick written by Estes in response to McElderry's request for flap copy, which Estes did not like to write (Dec. 30, 1977). The book was published in England by Oxford Univeristy Press, and there is correspondence with Antony Kamm, children's book editor; Oetinger Verlag in Hamburg was interested in the German rights. McElderry and Estes also discuss whether Estes will allow the Foundry Bookstore in New Haven, CT, to throw her a publication party. The final letter in the file discusses Estes's displeasure with some of Ayer's illustrations, as well as plans for The Moffat Museum, published by Harcourt, Brace & World in 1983. Personal topics include Estes's son-in-law Stephen's brain tumor, her husband's many health problems, and her cancelled 1978 trip to Madrid and Tangiers with a visit to authors Virginia Sorensen and Alec Waugh. McElderry and Estes also discuss the delay in McElderry's work after her husband's death, and the honorary degree she received from Mt. Holyoke College in 1978. There are also a number of letters between McElderry and Ayer, discussing Ayer's world travels and a sum of money she owed to McElderry.
- Penelope Farmer, 1971 - 1985
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1985